Preliminary Inventory to the George S. Reppas Papers, 1966-1982
Hoover Institution Archives
George S. Reppas Papers,
1966-1982
86038
Reppas, George S. (George Spiro), 1927-
111 manuscript boxes, 9 oversize boxes (52.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, correspondence, and business and legal records, relating to efforts of the Societe americaine grecque et malgache to establish a slaughterhouse and meat-processing plant in Madagascar, the forced bankruptcy of the company, the imprisonment of G. S. Reppas, efforts to secure his release, and his escape
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1986
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Corporations, American--Madagascar; Meat industry and trade--Madagascar; Madagascar--Economic conditions; Madagascar; Africa; United States--Foreign relations; Prisons--Madagascar
Preliminary Inventory
- SOBERI study of feed plant and feedlot abattoir (Box 1)
- Project sketch to potential investors (Jan 66). Includes:
  - Presentation of program for the industrial development of Morondava
  - Copy letter from Secretary General of Government reporting the approval of the Viande project by the Council of Ministers (Feb 4, 1996)
  - Copy of letter from Ministry of Agriculture confirming the cabinet's resolution to approve project (Feb 21, 66)
  - Various document on project presentation
- Application to Malagasy Government for approval of US loan (content same as presentation of project above)
- Cattle ranch and slaughtering operation, Investment Proposal, June 21 1968, Revised July 10 1968.
- Draft of application loan
- Proposal for plant construction and detailed design for abattoir facility by FMC, San Jose, California
- Summary of a beef slaughtering operation in Morondava. Appendix E is ground breaking ceremony with several translated speeches by Malagasy officials and articles on newspapers
- Application for AID extended risk guaranty, July 1967
- Plant blueprint and picture (Box 2)
- SOBERI correspondence 1968: signature of contract
- SOBERI correspondence 1970: discussions about delays and drafts
- SOBERI study of feedlot and feed plant
- Correspondence with Ministry of Industry, 1970: request for exoneration of taxes
- SOBERI correspondence 1969, 1971, 1972 (Box 3)
- Chart of accounts
- Correspondence OPIC 1969-71 for expiration and renewal of policy:
  - copy of foreign claims settlement commission document Dec 31, 1974
  - copy of letter from OPIC informing of expiration and cancellation of policy
  - request for re-registration July 13, 1971 to OPIC for a total of $2,115,000
  - application for insurance, Feb 12, 1969
  - handbook: OPIC coverage, Sept 1970
- USDA approved documents
- 4540.25 contracts with SOBERI:
  - SOBERI contract avenant no. 1, 2, 3, (no. 4 missing) and no. 5 unsigned
  - abattoir: specifications techniques
- 4540 SOBERI:
  - proces-verbal of temporary quantitative reception of abattoir Nov 3, 4, 1971
  - copy drafts for SOBERI
  - various correspondence with SOBERI
- Meetings: report on meetings with SOBERI
- SOBERI technical reports
- Plant engineering documents
- Correspondence with Nobel Peelman, SOBERI sub-contractor
- Draft memoire (Box 4, 5, 6)
- Christos Karkantzos correspondence plus few with SOBERI (Box 7)
- Bernard Pigny correspondence
- Mc Kinsey & Co. correspondence, 1968
- Telex and Cable correspondence of AGM
- Newspapers and magazines:
  - Newsweek article on Marshall's recall
  - Various Madagascar articles on AGM construction and contract signature
  - articles in international news about Madagascar politics, cattle industry, other cattle project in Madagascar and more.
- Correspondence Dr. Pas
- General engineering study of plant, 1971
- General documents. Includes: (Box 8 (Kelso Cotton))
  - attorneys working paper on suit against Swift and Morgan
  - copy application for land purchase to Malagasy State
- Keslo Cotton: draft for amendment to agreement with Morgan and Correspondence and invoices
- Correspondence with: (Box 9)
  - Honorine Ravony
  - Tsiranana (letter of 21 Mars 1972)
  - Resampa (letter of 19 June 72)
  - Proposal to Malagasy State: letter to General Ramanantsoa (8 June 1972)
  - Letter from Ministry of Finance telling that Madagascar will pay the SOBERI drafts
  - Letter from Directeur Tresor authorizing loan with Morgan
- Decrees:
  - Application for land and copy of Journal Officiel
  - Copies of decrees for international fund transfer and investment code regulations
  - Decree for SOBERI contract guaranty
- Malagasy meat inspection regulation
- Correspondence with Ministry of Finance, decrees and various documents on legislation and regulations
- Morgan letters following Releve de Conclusion to Ministry of Finance, Tsiranana on various programs to reorganize AGM (May 1971)
- Madagascar income tax files: balance sheet of AGM, 1971
- OPIC extended risk division: OPIC correspondence on renewal of policy, 1972, various correspondence between OPIC and AGM
- Letter to Christos in Prison for cooperation (Box 10)
- Copy telexes of San Francisco from Brad Jeffries to Maitre Lebel
- Ranch runaway study:
  - Various correspondence 1967-69 related to Viande, Dev, SOBERI, drafts and bank
  - Societe Melas engineering agreement
  - Correspondence between George and Bacopoulos for capital augmentation and contractor payment, July 19, 1972
  - Memo from George S. Reppas to Christos Bacopoulos on European transactions, draft payments, etc. Aug 25, 1972
- FMC preliminary design and proposal for abattoir, Feb 68
- Hellaby, New Zealand correspondence and profitability study 1972
- Blueprint
- Correspondence with various insurance company (personal) (Box 11)
- AGM Telephone message book
- Insurance policy
- Ledgers for fixed assets (Box 12)
- Business card collection-various
- Telephone logs
- Credit card charges and daily expenses receipts (Box 13)
- Insurance company invoices and correspondence (personal)
- Accounting reports from Tananarive
- Correspondences for meat regulation and standard
- Copy canceled checks AGM Viande San Francisco from 1966 to Oct 14, 1968 (Wells Fargo B.)
- Various accounting documents
- Canceled checks from Sep 13, 66 to January 31, 1972, AGM Viande San Francisco, Wells Fargo (Box 14)
- Canceled checks, Marathon Trade and Reppas Ranch (Box 15)
- Canceled checks AGM Development, 1968 to Sep. 30, 1971 (Box 16)
- Marathon fixed assets
- AGM accounting documents, files, banks, tax, correspondence, invoices, marketing data, contacts, etc. (Box 17, 18, 19)
- Documents of suit against Swift (Box 20)
- Claude Piveteau's financial expertise report
- Apologia to JDI and expertise
- Correspondence with Morgan
- Correspondence with Hellaby, New Zealand
- Wellaby project: letters of approval from Honorine and Raparison, correspondence
- Misc. check, copies of letter from Ray Sherwood
- Reppas correspondence with de Roux, Paris
- Proceedings in the AGM case appeal (translation notes taken by Embassy) (Box 21)
- Bradford letters to and from
- Correspondence from George S. Reppas to Bradford
- U.S. Court decision on AGM and Morgan, 1980
- Letters of support for George S. Reppas through Bradford (Box 22)
- Copy letters to Malagasy officials
- Doc. of Reppas vs. Morgan
- Doc. of Reppas vs. Swift
- Company documents: tax returns, banks, partnership, accounting, etc. (Box 23, 24, 25)
- Telex correspondence San Francisco, Tana and Athens (Box 26, 27, 28)
- Administrative files on staff (Box 29)
- The Support Materials folder contains (other folders uninteresting): (Box 30)
  - Various personal letters, letters from State Dep. to Mom, Bradford Jeffries, etc.
  - Pictures of Madagascar
  - various script for book writing
  - Madagascar Matin of May 16 1974, Choral group departure for the US
  - Various bay area articles
  - Madagascar Matin of period after Ratsimandarava and on AGM airplane theft
  - Fake French ID for escape
  - Certificat d'Identite delivered in Comorros
  - Articles about Andriatsitohaina 2 meat packing company in a Malagasy magazine
  - Copies of Roulleau letters
  - Sketches of table-bed
  - Ministry of Justice/ commissariat central daily check-in note pad
- Doc. 1975: contains copy of Cour de cassation decision, copy of foreign claim settlement commission of the U.S. (Box 31)
- Doc. 1974: contains declaration by Anthony Manikom about Bacopoulos' fund embezzlement, Apologia to JDI
- Doc. 1973: contains translation of Temporary Administrator Olivier Raparison's recount of the AGM affair, problems, and his actions
- Doc. 1972: contains bankruptcy decision of the Commercial Court
- Copies of various project documents (Box 32)
- Various correspondence from 1972 to 75
- Company documents: taxes, accounting, banks, etc. (Box 33)
- Paid invoices (Box 34)
- Status AGM, correspondence (Box 35)
- Various correspondence with OPIC, State Dep., AID for Viande (Box 36)
- Correspondence with OPIC 1971-1972
- Viande correspondence with Dep. of Commerce (Box 37)
- Correspondence with Dep. of Agriculture, Dep. of Labors, about regulations, etc. (Box 38)
- Correspondence with suppliers (Box 39)
- Correspondence and telexes AGM 1968-69 (Box 40)
- Bacopoulos letters, memos and correspondences
- Tana telex (Box 41)
- Various correspondence
- Tax return files
- Morgan loan agreement (Box 42)
- Swift sales representative agreement
- Management contract
- Swift and AID correspondence for OPIC coverage
- Correspondence
- Swift correspondence (Box 43)
- Morgan correspondence and loan
- Documents of Malagasy Ministry of Finance approving loan
- Verbal note from Malagasy Ministry of Foreign Affairs providing government guaranties for political risks of AGM
- Option agreement
- Loan agreement
- Copy of Madagascar Courrier and other articles on Madagascar in international press (Box 44)
- Pigny correspondence
- Greece correspondence
- Misc. correspondence
- Documents on the potential of various projects in Madagascar (Box 45)
- Correspondence with suppliers (Box 46)
- Files on SOMADELVA (Box 47)
- General correspondence and copy of demande d'agrement
- Misc. products and equipment presentation
- Swift and Morgan documents (Box 48)
- Aircraft and insurance documents and correspondence
- Letters to General Ramanantsoa (Box 49)
- Report of 1st appearance with JDI
- Report on meeting and discussions with Ranohisoa at the Bohemian Club
- Copy of Liebig proposal to Ramanitra
- Audited financial statements of AGM by Peat Marvick, July 1970
- Statement of Conclusion
- Letter to Dr. Roux providing evidences of US investment in Madagascar
- Articles of limited partnership
- Reppas general correspondence, Nov 72 to 1974 (Box 50)
- Copy correspondence AGM San Francisco 71-72 (Box 51)
- Misc. documents (Box 52)
- Swift and Bank of America Management documents (oct 1971)
- Sacet-Simmenthal-Ultrochi investment proposal in AGM
- Bank of America AGM financial statement report
- Ward Food files and joint-venture proposal (Box 53)
- Administrative files and correspondence for Viande Tana 67-68
- Administrative files and correspondence for Viande Tana (customers, suppliers, etc.) (Box 54, 55)
- Administrative files and correspondence for Marathon Trade (customers, suppliers, etc.) (Box 56, 57, 58)
- Corporate documents: investors, shareholders, etc. (Box 59)
- Correspondence with shareholders and investors (Box 60, 61)
- California Commissioner of Corporation (Box 62)
- Warrants
- AGM vs. Westinghouse
- Swift vs. Viande
- Viande vs. Swift and Morgan
- Morgan vs. GSR (72)
- Swift management contract and other contracts
- OPIC application for Swift
- Power of attorney for individual investors
- Qualification to do business in California (Viande) (Box 63)
- Distributor contract with South Western Petroleum Corporation
- Purchase agreement Marathon and Viande-Development
- Baker and McKenzie, attorneys: Memo on legal implication of drafts
- Correspondence with OPIC
- OPIC superseded application
- AGM California documents (Box 64)
- Other legal documents: individuals, ranch, etc.
- Correspondence, reports, meetings, documents about contractors, suppliers, customers, individuals, etc. (Box 65)
- Correspondence, reports, meetings, documents with Swift, ADL, George Fraise and other (Box 66)
- Correspondence, reports, meetings, documents with various individuals (Box 67)
- Amendment to partnership articles (Box 68)
- Correspondence, contracts and other documents about Malagasy Associates
- Limited partnership (Box 69)
- Malagasy associates
- Schedule of claims for principal and interests (Box 70)
- Creditor's claims
- Warrants
- Investors, creditors, notes
- Drafts of memoire (Box 71, 72, 73)
- Stock certificates (Box 74)
- Marathon Trade's statement of charges to AGM Viande (Aug 71 to 5 Sept 72) (Box 75)
- Viande accounts payable invoices
- Ward Food files (Box 76)
- Various records and general correspondence 66-68 (Box 77, 78, 79)
- Staff files (Box 80)
- Inactive investors files
- Various correspondence (Box 81)
- Inactive investors files
- Misc. correspondence with US attorneys (Box 82)
- SOBERI technical documents and plans for abattoir construction (Box 83)
- Copy Dossier d'Agrement presented to Ministry of Finance
- Swift agreement
- Supporting documents for memoire
- Corporate seals (Box 84)
- Minutes, articles, bi-laws (Box 85)
- AGM financial statements, July 70 (Box 86)
- Confidential report to investors, 1970
- Investment proposal documents
- Various correspondence (Box 87)
- Notes payable San Francisco
- Investment proposal documents (shares, loans, mortgages) (Box 88)
- Cattle ranch and slaughtering operations: investment proposal, January 3, 1969 version and March 15, 1970 version
- Copy document submitted for Dossier d'Agrement: Indicatif
- Application for extended risk guaranty, OPIC/USAID
- Ledgers (Box 89)
- Administrative documents
- Various AGM schedules and financial statements for startup, Oct 71 (Box 90)
- Law offices of Howard: legal documents about suit George S. Reppas and shareholders against Swift/Morgan. Contains:
  - Shareholder claim against Swift/Morgan
  - Swift management contract
  - Minutes of meeting of the board nominating Swift and ADL as members
  - Letters from Morgan to Tsiranana presenting reorganization plans (May 6 and 18, 1971)
  - Letter from Reppas commenting reorganization plan (Oct 8, 1971)
  - Letter of reaction of Morgan following Reppas comments (Oct 15, 71)
  - Morgan letter to Rabenoro, Emile Ramarosoana about reorganization (Oct 15, 71)
  - Copy of Swift study
  - Telexes about board meeting and shareholder meeting in San Francisco
- Staff files and applications for employment
- First mortgage documents (Box 91)
- Documents and drafts of investment proposal (Swift and Morgan)
- Plan manuals, Morondava
- Several schedules of AGM
- AGM Viande: principal and background materials, ADL (Box 92)
- Plans for Fermes and Usines, SOBERI
- Abattoir plans, technical specifications, blueprint, SOBERI (Box 93)
- Ledger MARATHON TRADE Co., Inc. (Box 94)
- Stock certificates (Box 95)
- OPIC application for individual investors (Box 96)
- Ledgers
- AGM Dev. minutes for board authorization to borrow money from Wells Fargo
- Stock certificates (Box 97, 98, 99, 100, 101)
- Marathon Production Inc.: articles, by-laws, minutes, journal, ledgers (Box 102)
- Viande: request for authorization for loan from AID. Contains note presenting the project to the Assembly of Madagascar, letters from Government approving the project (Feb 1966), and presentation of the plans.
- AID-OPIC application
- Feedlot project in Majunga area
- Barges prospectus and project
- Protocol of the agreement passed in Tana between Sacet and Ultrocchi with AGM (Jan 28, 1971) for exports to Italy.
- Kaiser: correspondence, meetings, reports, proposal to Madagascar for road construction (Box 103)
- ADL principal background materials for AGM
- Investment proposal, Viande, cattle ranching and slaughtering operation
- Financing proposal, Feb 1972
- Report first appearance with JDI (Box 104)
- Assignments, summons, requests, etc.:
  - Commercial court bankruptcy decision after trial, pronouncing bankruptcy of Viande, Dev, and Bacopoulos, no. 2594, Sept 5, 1972. Madagascar's claim: 4 first drafts to SOBERI paid (total 244,559,209 Fmg) plus taxes and duties unpaid (total 125,289,313 Fmg) for a total of 369,848,522 Fmg.
  - Request by Ministry of Finance to replace TA, followed by ordinance 2366 of July 5, 1972 appointing new TA with same court order as previous TA.
  - Request by new TA for experts assistance (July 5, 1972) followed by ordinance no. 2367 nominating OCCR INTERG and Claude Piveteau, both from France as experts (July 5, 1972). Ordinance presents their mission and order that a report be presented by Sept 15 1972.
  - Summons and assignment in payment issued to AGM (Aug 7, 1972)
  - Assignment in bankruptcy to appear in court (Aug 11, 1972)
  - Acte d'affectation hypothecaire and Acte d'affectation en nantissement, unsigned, undated. Estimated established after July 71, intended to be signed by AGM and Victor Miadana.
  - Summons, assignation en refere, to appear in court, asking for the nomination of a TA, and proposing his mission (July 9, 1971)
- Van Ommeslagh files, attorney, Belgium: working documents about bankruptcy matters, 1972. Contains:
  - Request to extend the power of TA to Development, to have access to all archives and records of the two companies, and for an extension of 3 months, followed by ordinance no. 2830 of Oct 11, 1972 granting that.
  - Commercial decision contesting the power of Maitre Boitard to represent AGM and stating that that power could only be exercised by the TA. (August 29, 1972)
  - Arbitration request against SOBERI presented by Van Ommeslagh in front of the Cour d'Arbitrage of the Chamber de Commerce International (undated). This document mentioned that:
    - 4 avenants were made to the SOBERI contract: Nov 21, 68; May 6, 69; July 8, 69; and Aug. 28, 69. The 5th avenant was intended for Nov 5, 1970 but apparently was not signed.
    - Reception provisiore quantitative by both parties effected between 26 April to May 7, 1971.
    - SOBERI required nomination of expert by the Malagasy court on Sept 17, 1971.
    - Malagasy court nominated 2 experts by ordinance no. 3111 on Oct 11 1971.
    - Reception quantitative des batiments et du materiel installe by the two experts and the parties on Nov. 3 and 4, 1971
    - Presentation of report by the experts on Jan 12, 1972
  - Report of the audit of the abattoir by the court appointed experts Aime Andriamanantena and Jacques Bompas (Jan 12, 1972)
  - Several letters and correspondences with Van Ommeslagh
- Boitard, Prompt, De Roux and Sherwood letters. Letters to Paul Prompt, Boitard's recommendation and counsel about the SOBERI drafts
- Judgment Tana: Ordinance 2274 on Sept 19, 1972 nominating TA as co-receiver and copy of commercial judgment pronouncing bankruptcy (Sept 5, 1972)
- Legal Tana Office: letters from TA and Honorine about Hellaby, letters to new TA, letters to Resampa, General Ramanantsoa, memo informing Malagasy government about Morgan Swift suit, original letter from Roulleau refusing access to Tsiranana, letters and reports to TA about various prospecting in Europe, etc.
- Several correspondence from TA, note to Henry Rakotoarivelo, U. of Calgary, Canada for financial plans to reinstate the AGM Viande operations, letters to Honorine to new TA, to Tsiranana, to General Ramanantsoa etc.
- Technical specifications, production standards, blueprints
- Correspondence with sudax suppliers (Box 105)
- Correspondence with TA and Ramaholimiaso, TWA, IFC, etc., invitation to TA to attend meeting in San Francisco in Dec 71
- Application for OPIC, July 1967
- Fish project in Madagascar
- Glass project in Madagascar
- Meat project in Ethiopia
- Personal letters, family letters (Box 106)
- AGM Projet de developpement industriel:
  - Note on startup of the project
  - Note (dated February 4, 1966) from the Secretariat General du Gouvernement to the Ministry of Agriculture, Interior and Industry confirming the Council of Minister's decision to approve the Viande project and granting authorization to proceed following their meeting on February 2, 1966
  - Letter from Jacques Rabemananjara, Minister of Agriculture confirming the Council of Minister's decision (dated February 21, 1966).
- AGM Viande and Swift contracts: folder containing copy of all contracts and agreements
- First mortgage doc, July 1971
- Info Madagascar Magazine: various economic news about Madagascar
- Prison correspondence from Jan 1974 to 1975 (Box 107)
- Prison correspondence from Nov 1972 to Dec 1973 (Box 108)
- various correspondence between 1968 and 71. Copy of 3 Roulleau letters, copy of letter to Ramananstoa (June 8, 1972), correspondence with Raymond Haizlip (68-69), commercial judgment.
- Copy of typed prison dairies, 2 volume. (Box 109)
- Raivo: A romance of Madagascar (Box 110)
- Madagascar Matin newspapers clippings and copies:
  - Oct 26, 1972: L'usine AGM en Conseil des Ministres
  - Nov 9, 1973: Le scandale AGM devant le tribunal aujourd'hui, (1 er jour)
  - Nov 10, 1973: Le scandale financier de l'AGM, (2e jour)
  - Nov 12, 1973: Une negligence coupable de la part du Gouvernement?, (3 et 4e j.)
  - Nov 13, 1973: Proces AGM, 4e jour hier, (5e jour)
  - Nov 14, 1973: Proces AGM, (6e jour)
  - Dec 1, 1973: Affaire AGM, toutes les parties ont interjete l'appel
  - Dec 22, 1973: Le pouvoir judiciaire mecontent
  - Mar 8, 1974: Affaire AGM en appel. Un temoignage tres attendu, (1 er jour)
  - Mar 11, 1974: Le scandale financier de l'AGM (3e jour), plus article on the abattoir
  - Mar 19, 1974: Mise en vente de l'abattoir AGM
  - Mar 23, 1974: Peines plus lourdes
  - Nov 13, 1974: L'avion de l'AGM a mysterieusement decolle dans la nuit
  - Mar 4, 1975. Victor Ramanitra removed from his position.
- Several photos, slides and negatives taken during trip to and in Comorros (Box 111, Folder Folder 1)
- Negatives home coming in SF
- Black and white 4" photos with several unidentified officials
- Negatives and photos of road to Majunga
- BW photos of 1975: FRS and Ratsimandrava cerceuil
- Personal photos
- Plant construction photos in BW and in color
- Copy articles in the San Jose Mercury News Sunday Magazine California Today: Escape from Malagasy, Sept. 7, 1975
- Article in the Oakland Sunday Tribune, June 26, 1977
- Loan contract papers between AGM and Morgan Guaranty Bank. Includes: (Folder Folder 2)
  - Contract agreements
  - Status AGM viande and development
  - Letters from Administrative secretary of AGM confirming authority of AGM officers
  - Letters from Bernard Pigny
  - Compte rendu loan to Direction du Tresor, Malagasy Government
  - Sales representative agreement between AGM and Swift worldwide
  - Loan agreement with Wells Fargo and Pledge agreement involving Swift
  - Copy application to Malagasy Government for the acquisition of the Morondava propriety
  - Copy decree giving the Malagasy Government guaranty to SOBERI loan (decree no. 68.490)
  - Copy contract between SOBERI and AGM